Finding Aid for Warren Petoskey papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Warren Petoskey papers 1873-2016 1990s-2016
Petoskey, Warren.
0.3 linear feet
1.4 GB online
1 archived websites online
2016048 Aa 2
Warren Petoskey is an Odawa and Lakotah elder. He is a writer, musician, dancer, and lectures on the history of American Indian boarding schools. The collection includes materials related to his professional and personal activities and interests, biographical and historical information, copies of genealogical records, as well as personal photographs and audio recordings.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Warren Petoskey (donor no. 11477 ), in March 2016.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The Warren Petoskey papers are open for research
Warren Donald Petoskey was born in Jackson, Michigan on June 3, 1945 to Warren Frank and Juanita Mae Petoskey. When he was 9 years old, Warren was given the name Biidassige, meaning "Light that is Coming", by his great-aunt, Ella Jane Petoskey after his great-great-grandfather, Ignatius Petoskey (for whom the city of Petoskey, Michigan was named). Warren is an elder of the Waganakising Odawa and Minneconjou Lakotah nations, member of the Bear Clan, and a citizen of the Little Traverse Bay Band of Ottawa and Chippewa Indians.
After attending a service at The Apostolic Church in Auburn Hills, Michigan Warren was spiritually moved and began following Christian teachings. This led to him becoming ordained as a Christian minister in 1971. While working as a certified addictions counselor, Spiritual Traditionalist Counselor, and House Manager in a Native treatment program, Warren noticed that there were core issues among every Native American client. These were issues that Warren had also experienced in his own life. He decided he would like to find a way to address the issues that he felt were residual effects in the Native American community from the American Indian boarding schools that so many were forced to attend.
In 1998, Warren founded and became the director of Dawnland Native Ministries, a traveling ministry that is based near Petoskey, Michigan. In Warren's own words, Dawnland Native Ministries is an outreach program that endeavors "to build bridges of understanding with all peoples regarding the damage done by America's boarding school policies and their effects on the current generations". He has traveled across the United States, mainly Michigan, with his wife, Barbara Louise Curton Petoskey, giving presentations regarding historical trauma and boarding school syndrome. Warren's father, Warren Frank Petoskey, and grandfather, Cornelius Joseph Petoskey, were among those forced into the boarding schools.
Warren Petoskey is a prolific writer of poetry and essays on his life as a Native American elder. In 2009, Warren published Dancing My Dream, a memoir that details his childhood, the stories of his family and ancestors, and gives a personal account of his spiritualism and way of life. Warren has also produced an album of Native American music, titled Sacred Dream, with music written and performed by him and his family members.
The Warren Petoskey collection, 1873-2016, contains correspondence regarding presentations that Petoskey has held and his professional performance, copies of genealogy and family records, writings -- including his poetry, essays, and his published memoir, Dancing My Dream, --photographs of himself and family members, certificates for language learning and earned in the course of his work as an addictions counselor, and other materials that document Warren's life as an Odawa and Lakotah elder. The collection also includes an oral history interview audio recordings, the contents of an audio CD, Sacred Dream, with Native American music written and performed by Warren Petoskey, and an archived website for Petoskey's ministry, Dawnland Native Ministries.
Subjects:
Indians of North America--Education.; Indians of North America--Michigan.; Ottawa Indians--Michigan.; Petoskey, Warren.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Indians of North America--Michigan.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Indians of North America--Michigan--Music.
Genre Terms:
Digital file formats .; Oral histories (document genres).; Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Web sites.
- Warren Petoskey
  - Biographical and historical information, 1787-1885, 1971-1972, undated (Box 1)
  - Certificates, 1972-2006 (Box 1)
    (scattered)
  - Correspondence, 1981-2016 (with gaps) (Box 1)
  - Dawnland Ministries Website, Archived Website
    (These versions were preserved by the Internet Archive and are made available through its Wayback Machine. The Bentley Historical Library is not involved in the collection or maintenance of this material.)
  - Event agendas and flyers, 2005-2015 (Box 1)
  - Lineage, 1873-2008 (with gaps) (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings and articles, 2012-2015 (Box 1)
  - Oral history interviews, 2016
    - May 13, 2016, .WAV file
    - July 5, 2016, .WAV file
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1)
  - Sacred Dream, undated, .ZIP file
  - Writings, 1995-2009, undated (Box 1)
Related Materials
The Bentley Historical Library provides a bibliography of resources that endeavors to list all manuscript collections in the library that reflect the history and culture of Native Americans in Michigan. The bibliography is available online at: http://bentley.umich.edu/legacy-support/nativeamericans/